# Stephen G Collins

3601 Kernan Blvd S, Jacksonville, FL 32224 (904) 438-9199

stephen@nibblesnbits.net https://nibblesnbits.net/

## FULL-STACK WEB APPLICATION DEVELOPMENT

Over ten years of successful software development experience with a reputation for meeting the most challenging organizational goals and objectives. A pragmatic and focused individual recognized for "making seemingly impossible situations work." A proven and verifiable record for:

- Producing higher performance standards and enhancing productivity during a period of shrinking budgets.
- Streamlining processes—constantly analyzing and reassessing existing methods to improve overall output.
- Controlling growth management—able to motivate and maximize productivity and employee morale without financial incentives.
- Developing and implementing highly successful strategic plans (short and long term).
- Maintaining up-to-date knowledge of every aspect of an organization—beyond the immediate job requirements

Professional Experience	Concurrent Projects
Guidewell/Florida Blue, Nov 2019 – Jun 2021	Ostrich, Oct 2020 – Present
	https://getostrich.com/
<b>SENIOR DEVELOPER</b> – Responsible for the development and maintenance of health plan management systems serving millions of customers across the country.	<b>TECHNICAL LEAD</b> – Responsible for the entire design and development process of financial accountability social platform.
Specific duties and responsibilities include:	Utilized multiple development technologies such as Node.js, Express.js, React, Relay, GraphQL, Material-UI Utilized Azure-based technologies such as App Services, Azure SQL, Azure DNS, and Application Insights
<ul> <li>Design, develop, and maintain both front and back- end applications using Node.js and React</li> </ul>	
<ul> <li>Develop proof-of-concept products using React with both GraphQL and REST APIs</li> </ul>	
ASG Results/National Auto Care, Mar 2019 – Oct 2019	Gomigo, LLC, Oct 2019 – Feb 2021
	https://gomigo.app/
<b>SENIOR DEVELOPER</b> – Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of vehicle service contract issuance site used by over 100 credit unions across the	<b>LEAD DEVELOPER</b> – Responsible for the entire design and development process of a social scheduling application.
country.	Utilized multiple development technologies such as Node.js,
Specific duties and responsibilities include:	Express.js, and React
<ul> <li>Design, develop, and maintain both front and back- end applications using C#, and ASP.NET MVC 5</li> </ul>	Utilized Azure-based technologies such as App Services, Azure SQL, MongoDB, Azure DNS, Azure Active Directory, Function Apps, Front Door, Azure CDN, Key
<ul> <li>Develop proof-of-concept products using C#,</li> <li>.NET Core, React and Azure</li> </ul>	Vault, Azure Cache for Redis, and Blob Storage
Fidelity National Financial, Mar 2018 – Mar 2019	<b>ECP, Inc.</b> July 2018 – Mar 2020
	https://opping.not/

**SENIOR DEVELOPER** – Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of multiple enterprise-scale systems responsible for processing over \$4 billion per year in Title and Escrow polices and fees.

Specific duties and responsibilities include:

- Design, develop, and maintain both front and backend applications using C#, jQuery, ASP.NET MVC and Web API hosted partially in Azure
- Document new and existing systems
- Manage remediation of application security analysis findings

https://ecpinc.net/

**CONSULTING DEVELOPER** – Responsible for the entire design and development process of a customer claim reporting system.

Utilized multiple technologies such as SQLite, jQuery, React, C#, and .NET Core

Utilized Azure DevOps for CI/CD process deploying to other hosted services

Centeva, LLC, Aug 2016 - Feb 2018

**SENIOR DEVELOPER** – Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of an n-tier Government Acquisitions Management system.

Specific duties and responsibilities include:

- Design, develop, and maintain both front and back-end systems for Government Acquisitions Management
- Integrating existing systems with third-party services
- Produce custom developer tooling for back-end systems management

# **PROJECTS**

Enterprise Service Bus for Department of Veterans Affairs:

Placed in charge of development for existing .NET 4.5 and SQL Server 2012 ESB, providing APIs and services for a
host of client applications

Client-facing Acquisitions Management applications:

- · Assisted in development of custom developed front-end for Acquisitions Management
  - o Inherited and maintained existing software from previous contracting customer
  - Revamped React/Redux-based existing UI and Web API 2 server functionality, resulting in 5-star ratings from government clients all over the country.

### Glimpse Live, LLC, 2015 - 2016

**FULL STACK WEB DEVELOPER** – Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of an n-tier Optometry and Dentistry business analytics platform.

Specific duties and responsibilities include:

- Spearheaded the design and development of full backend powering a modern client data extraction and analytics system
- Produced custom **developer tooling** for arbitrarily structured data analysis
- Gained skills in Agile development practices utilizing Atlassian JIRA software
- Utilized various Linux distributions within local VMs and AWS EC2 instances
- Managed Node.js application deployment with pm2 and nginx

## **COMPLETED PROJECTS**

Dentistry Business Analytics platform:

- Worked mostly unaided in development of all aspects of a fully custom business analytics platform.
  - O Designed MongoDB 2.6 and SQL Server 2014 underlying databases
  - Architected a Redis-based queue processing system for data transformation and analytics
  - Wrote custom queries and stored procedures for various CRUD operations
  - Developed front and back-end JavaScript and Typescript for client UI utilizing React, MongoDB, Express.js, and Node.js
  - Created and consumed JSON web services with Express.js and ASP.NET Web API
- Created and maintained .NET 4.5 client applications for data extraction

Optometry Business Analytics platform:

- Teamed up with developers and subject matter experts to create new revisions of Optometry EHR system data extraction services
  - O Developed from-scratch .NET 4.5 multithreaded data extraction service
  - o Performed maintenance on existing .NET 3.5 services

## RR Donnelley & Sons Company, 2012 - 2015

WEB APPLICATION DEVELOPER - Responsible for the design, development, and maintenance of over 50 individual client web sites, both back-end and front-end for a range of large financial institutions including T. Rowe Price and Washington Mutual.

Specific duties and responsibilities include:

- · Worked with development team to create new ASP.NET sites based on client requirements
  - Developed new applications in both ASP.NET WebForms and MVC platforms
  - Utilized both ADO.NET and Entity Framework for data access to a SQL Server 2008 database
  - Wrote custom queries and stored procedures for various CRUD operations 0
  - Developed font-ends using HTML5, CSS3, JQuery, and Bootstrap
  - Created and consumed web services with both WCF and Web API
- Maintained existing client sites, providing new and updated features as requested
- Developed new, fully customized internal reporting tools
  - Developed fully custom server and client-side UI controls
- Maintained up-to-date skills in new and emerging technologies
  - Gained knowledge in many server-side JavaScript products such as Node.js and MongoDB

## United States Air Force, 2008 – 2012

**AEROSPACE PROPULSION JOURNEYMAN** - Completed 4-year career with the U.S. Air Force. Gained management status above peers. Participated in the complete revitalization and overhaul of the EC-130H weapons system from the low status perceived in the past to the most powerful and effective Electronic Combat platform in history.

An active participant in the multiple cross-service contingency preparation exercises, and served a tour supporting combat missions in Operation Enduring Freedom. Part of a team that, during my service, received multiple servicelevel awards, including the Air Combat Command Maintenance Effectiveness award 3 consecutive years. A successful record for managing complex operations, supervising teams of people responsible for \$2.2 billion in assets.

# Precision Castparts Corporation, May - December 2007

**SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (Temporary Co-op)** - Maintained and developed Enterprise Resource Planning software managing \$300 million of inventory per year utilizing a SQL Server 2000/2005 and FoxPro-based backend, with Visual Basic 6 and C# 2.0 client and server-side applications. Responsible for "modernization" of ERP system by migrating existing client-side applications to .NET standards and architecture. Specific duties and responsibilities include:

- · Worked in three-man team in the development and maintenance of a VB6/FoxPro/SQL Server 2000-based **ERP** system for a major aeronautics industry parts manufacturer.
  - Solely responsible for upgrading existing VB6 and FoxPro application to .NET (C# and VB)
- Assisted team in implementation and integration of new VB6/SQL Server 2005-based ERP system by modifying existing applications as well as developing utilities for data migration.
- Proposed and subsequently assigned with setup/maintenance of new development environment
  - Performed setup and configuration (hardware and software) of source repository, file server, Exchange accounts for development/testing use, and isolated SQL Server instance
  - Developed bug reporting library and associated application

# \* Stephen Glynn Collins -- (904) 438-9199 -- sgcollins@outlook.com

# Additional Skills

Windows software development and testing with multiple languages and environments:

- · Nearly 20 years experience with Microsoft Visual Studio using VB.NET and C#
- 10 years experience in multiple web platform technologies including:
  - o ASP.NET WebForms, Web API, and MVC
  - o Node.js with Express.js and other libraries
  - Multiple front-end development tools: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, and a wealth of libraries.
- Experience with multiple .NET libraries and conventions: Windows Forms, ADO.NET, LINQ, Generics, TPL, and Visual Studio Tools for Office.
- Knowledge and experience with industry standard patterns & practices

Experience in SQL Server 2000 through 2016 setup and deployment

- · Contributed to implementation of large-scale ERP system
- Expertise in T-SQL and normalized database design

# Skilled in presenting clear and concise training

• Conducted several training courses in classroom and on-the-job settings in 10+ subjects

# Education

# DeVry University Online - Game and Simulation Programming

- · Pursued Bachelors in Applied Science.
- Maintained 3.6 GPA over 2 semesters; placed on DeVry University Dean's List both terms.

# Community College of the Air Force - Aviation Maintenance Technology

 Completed 39 credit hours towards associate's degree during time in service; continued education with DeVry University.

## East Central Technical College - Game and Simulation Programming

- Spent extra time during course learning ancillary skills in various programming languages and environments including Visual Basic 6 & 7, C# 1.0-3.0, and Java 6.
- · Gained experience in Windows system administration in enterprise environments